是, 大臣  第2季第5集
THE LAST FANTASY | TLF HALFCD TeaM
压制：beiming6@TLF  字幕：破烂熊
仅供交流  严禁商用
-=破烂熊字幕组=-
翻译:tpring 校对&时间轴:i1984
两害相权
真让人忍无可忍
It's absolutely intolerable.
是 大臣     当然 大臣
Yes, Minister. Quite so, Minister.
本来那些部门零敲碎打 各买各的文字处理设备
Each department about to order different word-processing equipment,
是我说服他们 由行政部出面下团购订单
and I persuaded them to place one big central order for everyone
金额大到能让英国厂家投资开发新设备
big enough for UK manufacturers to invest in systems development.
是 大臣     跟你们说也是白说
Yes, Minister. I don't have to tell you.
是白说 大臣
No, Minister.
谈判几个月 眼看就能发布特大新闻
Months of negotiation and we were nere a press announcement:
"哈克大力投资现代科技"
"Hacker's massive investment in modern technology."
"吉姆的国民工业信任票"
"Jim's vote of confidence in British industry."
"英国制造能行 吉姆说"
"'Britain can make it,' says Jim."
当然 大臣     是 大臣
Quite so.
布鲁塞尔突然发出指令 叫欧共体成员
And now this directive from Brussels saying all EEC members
全体遵循那些麻烦的欧洲标准
must conform to some niggling European word-processing standards
必须赞成欧共体委员会的计划
that we have to agree to the plans of committees
还要开欧洲文字处理设备大会 在布鲁塞尔
at the forthcoming Word-Processing Conference in Brussels.
哎 说话啊
Well, say something!
是 大臣     当然
Yes, Minister. Quite so.
就这样?
Is that all?
大臣 恐怕我们假装欧洲人 总得受点惩罚
That's the penalty we pay for pretending we're Europeans.
我完全明白您对欧洲的敌意
I fully understand your hostility to Europe.
我不像你 汉弗莱 我是亲欧洲 反欧共体
I'm not like you, Humphrey. I'm pro-Europe, just anti-Brussels.
有时我觉得你倒是反欧洲 亲欧共体
I sometimes think you're anti-Europe and pro-Brussels.
大臣 我既不亲谁 也不反谁
I'm neither pronor antianything.
我只是卑微的社会公器 盛放您深思熟虑的果实
I'm merely a humble vessel for the fruits of your deliberations
但可以看出 考虑到大欧洲理念的荒谬
It could be argued that given the absurdity of the idea,
欧盟已尽力辩不可辩之理
that Brussels does its best to defend the indefensible
行不可行之事     话不能这么说 汉弗莱
and make the unworkable work. That's not true, Humphrey!
不是我浮夸 靠着欧洲理念
Without sounding pompous
我们才能超越狭隘的国家利益
we must avoid narrow national self-interest.
一点都不浮夸     很好
It doesn't sound pompous... Good.
只是不准确罢了
Merely inaccurate.
听好了 卑微的社会公器
Listen, humble vessel,
欧洲各国本是一体 致力于同一个目标
Europe is a community of nations dedicated towards one goal.
什么这么好笑 汉弗莱?
May we share the joke?
大臣 我们客观地来看
Minister, let's look at this objectively.
这是各国利益的博弈场 我们为什么加入?
It's a game played for national interests. Why did we go in?
为了加强自由西方国家的联盟
To strengthen the free Western nations.
大臣 是为了离间德法 从而压倒法国
We went in to screw the French, splitting them from the Germans.
那法国呢?     为保护他们没用的农民免遭竞争
Why did the French? Protect their farmers from competition.
德国不是吧?     他们是为洗清种族灭绝的罪名
And the Germans? To cleanse themselves of genocide
请求重新加入人类社会
and apply for re-admission to the human race.
这也太尖酸刻薄了
I've never heard such cynicism!
那些小国总不是为自身利益吧?
The small nations didn't join for selfish reasons.
是吗? 卢森堡是为了赏钱
Really? Luxembourg is in it for the perks.
作为欧共体首都 外国资金滚滚而来
The EEC capital, all that foreign money pouring in.
他们本来就在中心位置
A sensible central location.
总部在布鲁塞尔 议会在斯特拉斯堡?
Administration in Brussels and Parliament in Strasbourg?
大臣 这就像把下院设在大西北
Minister! It's like having the Commons in Swindon
公务员放在中南部
the Civil Service in Kettering!
这么说 别的国家又图什么?     比如?
Why do other nations try to get in?
想想希腊
Take the Greeks...
我想不通希腊 尽管我对外国人一向很开明
Difficult to take the Greeks openminded as I am about foreigners
他们要什么? 橄榄山和松香酒湖
They'll want an olive mountain and a retsina lake.
我不信这些
I don't accept this!
对不起 大臣 您有些好朋友是希腊人?
I'm sorry. I suppose some of your best friends are Greeks?
很好笑
Very droll.
欧共体的问题不在国际合作 而在官僚主义
The problem isn't internationalism but too much bureaucracy.
可官僚主义正是国际合作的后果
The bureaucracy is a consequence of the internationalism.
不然为什么一名英国总长
Why else is there an English Commissioner,
下设一名法国主任 再往下又是一名意大利科长?
a French Director below him, an Italian Chef-du-Division?
我同意     这是巴别塔     我同意
It's like the Tower of Babel. I agree.
或者简直是联合国     我同意
Like the United Nations. I agree.
能插句嘴吗? 你们俩是不是彼此都同意?
If I may interject? You are in fact in agreement.
没那事
No, we're not.
典型欧共体官员什么样? 意大利人的组织能力
A Common Market official has the organising of the Italians,
德国人的弹性 法国人的谦逊
the flexibility of the Germans, the modesty of the French,
再加比利时人的想象力 荷兰人的慷慨
the imagination of the Belgians, the generosity of the Dutch
还有爱尔兰人的智力水平
and the intelligence of the Irish!
而且还是个保险箱     怎么讲?
It's all a gravy train! How do you mean?
喝香槟 吃鱼子酱 公家豪华轿车 私人飞机
Live on champagne and caviar, Mercedes, private aeroplanes.
个个都伸嘴在食槽里拱
Every official has his snout in the trough
大多数人连前蹄也伸了进去
most of them their trotters as well!
抱歉我不同意 布鲁塞尔的人都是辛劳的公仆
Brussels is full of hard-working public servants
他们整日奔波 忍受无聊的招待
enduring exhausting travel and tedious entertainment.
是无聊哦 干掉那么多熏鲑鱼 灌进那么多香槟酒
Working their way through smoked salmon and all that champagne
大臣 反正错不在他们     怎么讲?
You're blaming the wrong people. What do you mean?
是您某位内阁同僚把团购计划捅到欧共体
One of your Cabinet colleagues warned Brussels of your plan
所以指令才来得这么快
which is why the directive appeared so quickly.
内阁同僚? 不用说 又是那个死科贝
Cabinet colleagues? Don't tell me! Bloody Corbett again!
每当想到科贝 我都替犹大喊冤
When I think of Corbett, I warm to Judas Iscariot!
对 确实是工商大臣捅的
Yes, it was the Secretary of State for Trade and Industry.
那个背信弃义 刚愎自用 好大喜功的小人
Treacherous, disloyal, arrogant publicity-seeking creep!
对不起 说得太难听了
I'm sorry if that sounds harsh.
正相反 大臣
No, Minister
比起他常任秘书的评价 您这算赞歌了
Compared to what his Secretary says that's a generous tribute.
他怎么做到的?     谁知道?
How did he do it? Who knows?
晚报上有 大臣
The evening paper, Minister.
每当科贝靠近 我都觉得背后挨了一刀
Whenever Corbett comes near me I feel stabbing pains in the back
干吗给我这个 伯纳?
Why did you give me this, Bernard?
在这里     哦
Just there. Oh, yes.
天啊 内阁改组
Good God! Cabinet reshuffle!
"有消息称 首相将宣布内阁重大变动"
"It's rumoured that the PM will announce Cabinet changes
"就在本次会议期间"
"before the end of the present session."
我怎么不知道? 他们怎么知道? 真的假的?
Why didn't I know about this? How do they know? Is this true?
大臣 我只是一介公务员 不参与这种高层变动
I'm a humble civil servant, do not move in such exalted circles
不像内阁大臣和记者
as Cabinet Ministers and journalists.
确实是真的?     真的
But is it true? Yes.
你怎么知道 你不是不参与么?
How do you know?
我是说 真的有这个消息
I mean, it's true that it's rumoured.
内阁改组 我才刚开始着手我的...我们的...
Cabinet reshuffle I've hardly started the things that I...we...
也许不会动您 大臣
Perhaps you won't be moved, Minister.
不动的话 我的事业也就不会前进了
Ah... If I'm not, it means my career isn't moving forward
至少它不会倒退
At least it's not moving backwards.
倒退? 你不是说...天啊 可我...
Backwards? You don't mean...? Good God! But I...
该不会...会不会...我干的还不错吧?
It's not... I mean, it's... I've been doing all right, haven't I?
我们还不错吧?     您干的不错
We've done all right? You've done all right.
我们还不错吧 伯纳?     是 大臣
We've done all right? Yes, Minister.
就算我称不上功臣 可也不算失败
I may not be the outstanding success, but I'm not a failure.
大臣 您干的不错     其实我挺成功的
You've done all right. I've been quite successful.
如果马丁去财政部 我可能调去管外交部
If Martin were moved to Treasury, I could get Foreign Office!
可能吧
Perhaps you might.
你也拿不准啊     拿不准
You don't sound very certain. I'm not.
你有什么消息?     没消息 所以我才拿不准
What have you heard? Nothing, it's why I'm not certain.
卡弗怎么知道?     也许他说话首相听得入耳
Why does Bob Carver know? Perhaps he has the PM's ear.
首相把他揣在兜里     首相的耳朵还真长
He's in the PM's pocket. Then the PM must have a large ear.
好 这事咱们先不操心     好 大臣
Right, well... Let's not worry about it any more.
放下不谈了     是 大臣 我是说不谈了
We'll say no more about it. Yes, Minister. I mean, no, Minister.
急也是干着急 对吧?
There's no point worrying about it, is there?
根本就没什么可急的吧?     是 大臣
Nothing to worry about, is there? No, Minister.
好吧大臣 参加布鲁塞尔大会吗? 我觉得应该去
Shall we attend the Brussels conference? We should.
可如果首相要调动弗雷德...
But if the PM should move Fred...?
参不参加布鲁塞尔大会?
Shall we attend the conference in Brussels?
什么会?     文字处理设备
What? Word-processing.
哦 改组之前还是之后开?
Ah! Well, does it take place before or after the reshuffle?
谁知道?     算了 我听过这种事
Who can say? Well, no. I've known this happen before.
今天你不在其位 明天就不在位了
One day you're out of your office the next you're out of office.
这不是出国乱转的时候
This is no time for an idiotic foreign junket!
大臣 您不能为改组提心吊胆
Minister, you mustn't allow the reshuffle to prey on your mind.
我才没有提心吊胆
It's not preying on my mind.
我根本就不想它了     太好了
I'm not thinking any more about it. Splendid.
伯纳 6点来改组院...洗牌院...下院见我
Meet me at 6 o'clock in the House of shuffles...cards...Commons
晚上好 汉弗莱爵士     晚上好 少校
Good evening, Sir Humphrey. Good evening, Major.
阿诺德 改组的事几时能定?
Arnold, when will we know about the reshuffle?
还得等一阵
A little while yet.
我们部有什么消息吗?
Any news yet about my department?
得了 汉弗莱 我只是内阁秘书
I'm only Cabinet Secretary
又不是旗帜报政治通讯员
not political correspondent of the New Standard.
对我的大臣评价如何?
But how does my Minister stand?
首相似乎认为他干的不错
I think the PM feels he's done all right.
不过有个动向很有意思
But there's been an interesting development.
嗯?     嗯...
Mmm? Mmm.
啊
Aahh!
什么?
What?
布鲁塞尔问他有没有空担任下届总长 只要他愿意
Brussels have asked if he'd be available for commissionership
他总归是亲欧洲派嘛
After all, he's a good European.
当然这都属于机密
In strict confidence, of course.
是要给他和平免职吗?
Is he being gently eased out?
汉弗莱爵士 阿诺德爵士
Sir Humphrey, Sir Arnold.
你来了 伯纳
There you are, Bernard.
好 喝杯咖啡如何 伯纳?
Right. Would you like a coffee, Bernard?
谢谢     一起坐坐 来杯咖啡
Thank you. Pull up a chair.
伯纳 换个大臣你觉得怎样?
Well, Bernard, how do you feel about having a new Minister?
你是说他...     不 汉弗莱爵士是在假设
You mean, he's... No, Sir Humphrey is conjecturing.
当然 我会很遗憾的
Ah, of course, I'd be very sorry.
怎么了 你不会吗?
Er... Why? Wouldn't you?
当然不会
Of course not!
可他开始拿得起工作了啊     正是
But he's getting a grip on the job. Exactly!
拿得起工作的大臣是祸害
Ministers with a grip on the job are a nuisance.
会提出争论     大臣都争论
They argue. All Ministers argue.
拿得起工作才危险 他们可能是对的
There's a real danger they'll be right.
你告诉他们这事不可能 他们会挖出过去的报告
One tells them something is impossible, they dig out an old paper
里头你写着这事很好办 真无聊
in which one had said it was easy very tedious.
把他们送走 你就可以彻底清盘 从头调教新人
Once they've gone, one can start with a new boy.
改组真是一件盛事 首相也喜欢
Wonderful things, reshuffles. And Prime Ministers like them too.
干净利落 赶着大家团团转
Fresh, decisive, keeps everyone on the hop.
只有大臣们最慌张
Only Ministers panic about them.
有意思 能不能让大臣固定不动
Wouldn't it be interesting if Ministers were fixed
常任秘书改来改去?
and Permanent Secretaries were shuffled around.
那样的话 伯纳 会给整个体制致命一击
That, Bernard, would strike at the very heart of the system
直至动摇不列颠的国本
that has made Britain what she is today.
天长地久才是权力
Power goes with permanence.
变幻无常让人无力     轮流上台等于阉割
Impermanence is impotence. Rotation is castration.
是该让他们轮上一轮了
It's time they all had a little spin.
没错 可民主要求...
Yes, but surely in a democracy...
谢谢 伯纳 没你事了
Thank you, Bernard, that'll be all.
对 可我的...     谢谢 伯纳
Yes, but I've only... Thank you, Bernard.
好的 谢谢 汉弗莱爵士
Yes, thank you, Sir Humphrey.
晚安 阿诺德爵士
Good night, Sir Arnold.
如果你们大臣真去了布鲁塞尔 也别高兴得太早
If he does take Brussels, I wouldn't get out the champagne
怎么讲?      关于他的接班人有些风声
What do you mean? There is talk of his possible successor.
谁?
Who?
我不知该怎么告诉你 可是...
I don't know how to put this, but, well...
巴希尔·科贝
...Basil Corbett.
你怎么了 亲爱的? 吉姆?
What's the matter, darling? Jim?
吉姆     对不起
Jim! I'm sorry.
出什么事了?     没事
Something wrong? No, nothing, really.
肯定有事
Something is.
报纸上全是改组的消息
The papers are full of a reshuffle.
真的假的?     我不知道
Are they true? I don't know.
怎么 你在内阁啊     内阁总是最后知道
You're in the Cabinet. We're the last to find out.
不能问首相吗?     当然不能
Can't you ask the PM? Of course not.
怎么不能?     就是不能
Why not? Well... I just can't.
别人会以为我在发慌呢      这样啊
It would look as if I were insecure. I see.
不知是好事还是坏事 不知我要上还是要下
whether it's good or bad news, whether I'm up or down.
还是照例原地打转
Or round and round.
也不知我算成功还是失败
I don't know whether I'm a success or failure.
你觉得呢?     我觉得你干的不错
What do you think? I think you've done all right.
不错行吗?     我不知道 行吗?
Is that good enough? I don't know.
我不知道 行吗?     我不知道
I don't know, is it? I don't know.
说不准 也许首相嫌我太成功
The PM might think I've been too successful.
你知道 威胁到他的权威
You know, a challenge to the leadership.
你?
You?!
不是我 是马丁加上我的支持
No, not me, but Martin with my support.
你看 如果首相要铲除异己
If the PM is standing by to repel boarders,
又不能安稳地撵走马丁
and Martin can't be got rid of safely
外交大臣确实不好撵走 当然得拿我开刀了
as Foreign Secretary, I'm the obvious one for demotion.
孤立马丁     会送你去哪呢?
Isolate Martin. Where would you be sent?
挂名闲差多得是
There's no shortage of useless non-jobs.
枢密院长 掌玺大臣 体育部长
Lord President, Lord Privy Seal... Minister of Sport...
旱灾涝灾特派员
...with special responsibility for droughts and floods.
没准你会升职呢 亲爱的
Maybe you'll get promotion, darling.
也许吧 别忘了巴希尔·科贝
Maybe... Don't forget there's Basil Corbett.
他专门跟我过不去     他跟谁都过不去
He's out to get me. To get everyone.
他是个尖牙利齿死鱼眼 两面三刀的小人
He's a smooth-tongued, hard-nosed, cold-eyed, two-faced creep.
他为什么这么吃香?
Why's he so successful?
因为他是个尖牙利齿死鱼眼
Because he's a smooth-tongued, hard-nosed,
两面三刀的小人
cold-eyed, two-faced creep.
还有呢?     他电视形象不错
Apart from that? He looks OK on TV.
你也是啊     是吗?
So do you! Do I?
对     你说真的?
Yes! Really mean that?
对     你太好了
Yes. What a nice thing to say!
我和科贝彼此掣肘 挤来挤去
I've got to elbow Corbett or he'll elbow me.
手肘 政坛上最有力的武器
Elbows, the most important weapon in a politician's armoury.
除了正直之外     正直?
Other than integrity. Integrity?!
喂?
Yes?
哪位? 等等 是布鲁塞尔的加斯顿·拉罗
Who's speaking? Hold on. It's Gaston Larousse from Brussels.
布鲁塞尔?
From Brussels?
晚上好 专员(法语)...专员
Bonsoir, Commissionaire... Commissar...
对(意大利语)
Si...
非常有意思
That's very interesting.
请容我考虑一下
I shall need a little time to think about it.
我非常荣幸
I'm very honoured.
10号(意大利语)知道你在通知我吗?
Does Numero Dix know you're talking to me about this?
10号
Number 10.
唐宁街
Downing Street.
这样啊 那你给我留个家里电话
I see... Tell you what, give me your home telephone number.
好
Yes...
我会尽快答复你 非常感谢 再见
I'll give you a ring very soon. Thank you very much, goodbye.
什么事?
What was that?
我不知道     什么叫不知道?
I don't know. What do you mean?
他们要提名我担任英国驻欧共体专员
They want me as one of Britain's commissioners for the EEC.
什么意思?     搬家去布鲁塞尔呗
What does it mean? Living in Brussels.
不不 我是说 这是什么意思?
No, I mean, what does it mean?
10号知道了 那就是和平撤我职?
Number 10 knows, so is it a plot to ease me out?
是巧合? 是暗示? 究竟什么意思?
Is it just a coincidence? What does it mean? Is it a hint?
首相想让我光荣隐退?
Is the PM giving me a face-saving exit?
或者跟首相无关 本来就要派我去?
Or was the post coming up anyway?
某种方面说...是挺光荣的
It's a great honour... in a way.
这职位怎样?     惨透了
Is it a good job? Terrible.
跟英国政治完全隔绝
It's curtains as far as British politics is concerned.
比领爵位还惨 永世不得翻身
It's worse than a peerage. Absolute failure, total failure.
要想回来 除非自己建个党
You're reduced to forming a new party if you want to get back.
这工作具体干什么?
What does the job involve?
身处恐怖的欧共体官僚中心 进了保险箱
The heart of that ghastly Brussels bureaucracy, the gravy train.
每年薪水5万磅 报销2万磅
50,000 a year salary, 20,000 a year expenses.
香槟 龙虾 周游列国 高级酒店
Champagne, lobsters, foreign travel, luxury hotel...
豪华轿车 私人飞机
...private limousines, private aircraft...
午休时间
...siestas in the afternoon...
比利时海滩度周末
...long weekends at Knocke-le-Zoute...
我们去看看吧?      好啊
We should go over and have a look. Why not?
偶尔失败一下也不错
Sometimes we deserve a bit of failure.
内阁要改组 先生?
Going to be a reshuffle, sir?
对 从旗帜报上看来的吧
Yes, I suppose you saw that in the Standard.
对 先生     我也是
Yes, sir. So did I, actually.
当然 我几个星期前就听说了 先生
I first heard it a couple of weeks ago, sir.
是吗?     是 先生
Did you? Yes, sir.
其实我也是 听说什么?
So did I, really. Where did you hear it?
司机都知道了     怎么知道的?
All the drivers knew. How?
听首相的司机说的
From the PM's driver.
还有内阁秘书的司机     哦 对
The Cabinet Secretary's driver. Oh, yes.
还听说什么?     就是那些
What else did they hear? Just the usual.
科贝要提拔了 首相不能再忽略他
Corbett's in line for promotion, PM can't overlook him.
显然 老弗雷德...抱歉 是就业大臣
Apparently, old Fred the Employment Secretary, sorry, sir -
他会被明升暗降 踢到上院去
he's going to get kicked upstairs.
他们怎么知道?     他换司机了
How do they know? His driver's been re-assigned.
关于我有什么消息?
What's the gossip about me?
还真没什么消息 先生
Well, nothing really, sir.
没有?     没有
Nothing? No.
我们都说不出个所以然来
We don't know what to make of that.
您有消息吧 先生?     我当然有
You'll know, won't you, sir? Yes, of course.
不过 当局者迷 旁观者清
Sometimes it's difficult to know about oneself.
就是 我到底有多成功...
You, know, just how successful...
你们圈子里...有没有...?
What do your mates say... about...?
都说您干的不错 先生
They all think you've done all right, sir.
伯纳 我有点进退两难     我能帮忙吗 大臣?
I'm in a bit of a quandary. Can I help, Minister?
内阁洗牌的事要下注了
It's this reshuffle that's on the cards.
非常巧妙 大臣
That's very witty, Minister!
对不起 我以为您在讲...请继续
I'm sorry, I thought you were making a... Do please carry on.
更麻烦的是 他们请我去做欧共体专员
To complicate matters, I've been asked to be an EEC Commissioner.
很好啊     好吗 伯纳? 这就是问题
Very nice. Is it nice, Bernard?
伯纳 你跟我说实话
Bernard, tell me, quite frankly...
我在这当大臣 是不是当的不错?
...as Minister here, do you think I've done all right?
是啊大臣 您确实不错
You've done all right.
你看 汉弗莱到处拦我的路
Humphrey's blocked me on so many issues.
从来没有诚心诚意站我这边
He's never really been on my side.
老实说 "不错"其实不算好吧?
To be honest, "all right" isn't really good enough, is it?
这个 它算...不错
Well, it's... all right.
你听到...什么小道消息吗?
Have you... er... heard anything... on the grapevine?
关于您?
About you?
没什么消息 大臣
Nothing really, Minister, no.
只说英国驻欧洲专员发了封电报
Only that the British Commissioner in Europe sent a telegram
给外交部和内阁欧洲委员会
to the FCO and the Cabinet Committee on Europe.
是布鲁塞尔提出请您做专员
The idea for you to be a Commissioner came from Brussels,
但终归得首相任命
but it is a Prime Ministerial appointment.
首相已经跟外交部长和内阁秘书谈过
The PM discussed it with Foreign Secretary and Cabinet Secretary
并且同意他们探探您的口风
and cleared the way for you to be sounded out.
首相府和财政部都相信您会接受
As it's believed at Number 10 and Number 11 that you might accept
还问了内阁里的某人愿不愿接您的班
a colleague has been sounded out about becoming Minister here.
恐怕我知道的就这些
I'm afraid that's all I know.
没别的了?
No more than that?
问谁愿不愿接我的班?
Which colleague has been sounded out to take my place?
伯纳 如果我不去欧洲...
Bernard, if I were not to go to Europe...
不 如果我去...不 如果我不去
No, if I did go... No, if I were not to go to Europe,
我会升还是降?
would I go up or down?
汉弗莱爵士要来开会了 大臣
Time for your meeting with Sir Humphrey, Minister.
喂 好的     什么事?
Yes, fine. What's it about?
去不去文字处理设备大会的事
The visit to the word-processing conference.
文字处理设备大会?
The word-processing conference?
汉弗莱 告诉你个好消息 我改主意了
Humphrey, you'll be pleased to hear that I've changed my mind,
我确实应该去布鲁塞尔
I shall be going to Brussels after all.
您要辞掉行政部的职位?
You're resigning from the Department?!
不不不 我要参加文字处理设备大会
No, I'm talking about this word-processing conference.
这样啊     我还是想去布鲁塞尔转转
I see. I would like to see Brussels.
理由呢?     没理由不去
Why? Why not?
是没理由不去 可理由呢?
Why not, indeed, but why?
我好奇嘛     您是挺好奇的 大臣
I'm a curious person. You certainly are.
我昨天言重了
I've been a little hasty.
你对布鲁塞尔的辩护很有说服力
Your arguments on behalf of Brussels were thoroughly convincing.
大臣 我又回味了一下您的观点
Minister, I've been reflecting on your views,
您对布鲁塞尔的批评非常明智
and I find wisdom in your criticism of Brussels.
您暗示的腐败和...     不不不
You implied it is corrupt and... No, no, no.
大臣 求您...     不对 汉弗莱
Minister, please... No, Humphrey.
是你说服了我
It is you who have convinced me.
我现在相信 布鲁塞尔都是敬业的官员
I'm now convinced that Brussels is full of dedicated men,
肩负着四处奔波 公关接待的重担
all bearing a heavy burden of travel and entertainment.
奢侈是工作需要
They need all that luxury.
喝喝小酒
The odd drinky!
鱼子酱 香槟 私人飞机 豪华轿车?
Caviar and champagne, private planes, air-conditioned Mercedes?
这是外交的润滑油
It oils the diplomatic wheels.
伸嘴拱食?
Snouts in the trough.
别说的这么难听     对不起 真不知我跟谁学的
That's not an attractive phrase I can't think where I picked it up
我们都去布鲁塞尔开会 说定了?
We'll all go to this conference, agreed?
大臣 您改主意完全因为我的话?     当然是
Is your change of heart due to my arguments? Of course.
不是因为传说中布鲁塞尔专员的职位?
It's nothing to do with the rumour of your post in Brussels?
汉弗莱 你怎么能这么想
That thought is not worthy of you.
世上还有正直这回事
There is such a thing as integrity.
好的 谢谢
Oh, yes, thank you.
科贝 你不能让科贝这种人...
Corbett! You can't let someone like Corbett...
不能让科贝这种人管我们部
You simply can't let Corbett loose on the department.
这是灭顶之灾 不管你跟他说什么
It'd be disastrous. Everything one says to Corbett
明天一早准上太阳报
appears in the Sun the next morning.
很高兴你还读太阳报 (煽情小报 三版有裸女)
Glad to know you read the Sun.
你一定要制止 阿诺德 我求你
You must stop it, Arnold, I implore you.
我又不是首相
I'm not the Prime Minister.
可实际控制改组的是你吧
It is really you who arranges the reshuffles.
不 如果首相真决定任命谁
No, if there's an appointment the PM is set on,
内阁秘书只能勉为其难地照办
the Cabinet Secretary must reluctantly acquiesce.
大方向上是你掌舵吧
You do keep your hand on the tiller.
如果哈克拒绝欧共体职位
If Hacker decides to turn down Brussels,
科贝就不那么容易去你们部
it would be easier to keep Corbett away from your department.
问题就在这里 他打算接受欧共体职位
This is the trouble, he'll take Brussels.
哦     是啊 我知道
Oh. Yes, I know.
他说他相信大欧洲理念
He says he believes in the European ideal.
对 我知道 我知道
Yes, I know, I know.
政客职业病嘛 会上自己的当
Politicians get taken in by their own speeches.
你也有错 汉弗莱 你三天两头泼他冷水
This is partly your fault. You've blocked Hacker time and again.
都是为了政府好 阿诺德
Only in the interests of good government, Arnold.
那当然 不过你最好让他这两天出点成就
Quite. But what you need is a big success in the next few days.
出点成就?     对
A big success? Yes.
就这两天?
The next few days?
这样我...首相就有充分理由留下他
That would give me, give the PM a good case for keeping him here.
然后 就好把科贝调到就业部去了
Then, we might be able to move Corbett to Employment.
弗雷德非撤不可吗?
Is Fred definitely going?
对 他老在内阁会议上打瞌睡
Yes, he keeps falling asleep in Cabinet.
我以为他们都打瞌睡
I thought they all did.
对 不过总不至于在说话的时候
Yes, but not while they're actually talking.
汉弗莱 有消息吗?     什么消息 大臣?
Ah, Humphrey! Any news? Of what, Minister?
当然是内阁改组     没有
The Cabinet reshuffle. No.
你中午不是和内阁秘书吃饭了吗?
Didn't you have lunch with the Cabinet Secretary?
对     有什么结论?
Yes. What came up?
眼下没结论
Nothing as yet!
我只知道改组的事周一公布
All I know is the reshuffle will be announced on Monday.
您有消息吗?     什么消息?
Have you any news? Of what?
专员的事 您去不去布鲁塞尔?
The Commissionship. Are you going to Brussels?
这个...
Well...
作为议员来说 我觉得不该去
With my Parliamentary hat, I don't think it would be a good idea.
不过作为内阁大臣 我觉得应该去
With my Cabinet hat on, it would be a good idea.
而作为党派成员 该去也不该去
With my party hat on, there could be arguments on both sides.
懂了 您到底把自个当什么?
Which hat are you talking through now?
您决定要去布鲁塞尔了?     是也不是
Have you decided about going to Brussels? Yes and no.
您在犹豫什么呢 大臣?      我不知道
What are the pros and cons, Minister? I don't know.
我以前可能没说过
I haven't said this before,
但这取决于我是不是还不错 你们说呢?
but it depends on whether I've done all right. What do you think?
您确实不错
You've done all right.
如果我真的不错 那就错不了
If I've done all right, that's all right,
我得留下 结果应该还不错
I shall stay because I'll be all right.
可如果我只是不错 留下就错了 没错吧?
But if I've only done all right, to stay would be wrong, right?
大臣 我有个建议
Minister, I have a suggestion
为稳妥起见 您得做出点成就
to be on the safe side, you need a big success.
可不是     大获全胜那种     对
Yes. A triumph, in fact.
得提升个人形象 做出一大政绩
You need some publicity for a great political achievement.
对对 你有什么主意?     我不知道 我正在想
What have you in mind? I'm trying to think of something.
多谢你 帮大忙了 干吗突然要政绩?
Thank you, that's a great help. What's the purpose?
午餐时确实有些结论
Something did come up at lunch.
阿诺德爵士说有了这么个胜利
Sir Arnold feels that with this triumph,
首相就不好给您降职
the PM couldn't move you downwards,
伯纳和我就有幸能把您留在身边
Bernard and I have the good fortune of you staying on with us.
不可能给我升职吗?
So there's no chance of moving up?
哦...
Ooh...
可惜啊 大臣 没有
Sadly, Minister, alas.
人还是现实点好     好吧
One must be a realist. Oh, well.
就这么办 我得去布鲁塞尔了
That's it, it's got to be Brussels.
且慢 我想到了
No, wait a minute. I've got an idea.
如果您不搭理欧共体
Supposing you ignore the EEC.
照样发表您的设备团购计划
Publish your own plans for word-processing machines...
给英国厂家下大笔订单
...with big orders for British manufacturers...
马上 明天就发
...starting immediately. Tomorrow.
一定要赶在周一之前
Certainly before Monday.
增加工作岗位 增加投资
Involving more jobs, more investment.
增加出口订单     增加选票
More export orders. More votes.
对 到时候会增加的
Yes, when the time comes.
我们不能挑战欧共体指令     其实不是指令
We can't defy an EEC directive. It isn't a directive.
还没正式签发 目前只是请求
It hasn't been ratified, it's merely a request.
我们不能对欧洲友邦背后捅刀子 当面吐口水
We can't stab our partners in the back and spit in their face.
您对谁也不能背后捅刀子又当面吐口水
You can't stab anyone in the back while spitting in their face.
话说回来 挑战布鲁塞尔就会...
On the other hand, defying Brussels would be...
大受欢迎
Very popular!
还证明我能够掣肘他
And prove I had elbows.
什么?
What?
手肘 手肘
Elbows, elbows!
可是     可是什么 大臣?
But... But what?
我就得放弃那些...
I'd have to give up all that...
食槽     对
Trough. Right.
事到临头 人总得以本国为重
When it comes down to it, one's own country must come first.
太对了
How true.
尽管严格说来 这不算政府事务 大臣
And, although, strictly, this isn't a Government matter,
您走了我个人也会痛惜之至
I, personally, would be deeply sorry to lose you.
是吗 汉弗莱 你说真的?
Really, Humphrey, is that true?
千真万确 大臣 绝对是肺腑之言
Yes, I mean that, Minister, most sincerely.
你太好了 汉弗莱 我们彼此是有些好感
I suppose we have got fond of one another.
某些方面      某些方面 对
In a way. In a way, yes.
就像恐怖分子和他的人质
Like a terrorist and his hostage.
你们俩谁是恐怖分子?
Which is the terrorist?
他是
He is!
好的 伯纳 就这么定了
Right, OK, Bernard, that's the decision.
通知媒体好吗?     是 大臣
Inform the press!
告诉我 汉弗莱 如果我走了谁会接班?
Tell me, Humphrey, who would have got my position?
我不知道
I don't know...
您不是说是巴希尔·科贝吗?
Didn't you tell me it was Basil Corbett?
巴希尔·科贝?
Basil Corbett?!
原来如此 巴希尔·科贝
I see, Basil Corbett.
是 大臣
Yes, Minister.